<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<preface version="5.0" xml:id="pre.quick"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>What is &productname; &productnumber;?</title>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <para>
 &suse; &productname; is a Cloud-Native Computing Foundation (CNCF) certified
 &kube; distribution on top of &suse; &mos;.
 &suse; &mos; is a minimalist operating system based on &sle; 12 SP3, dedicated
 to hosting containers. &suse; &mos; OS inherits the benefits of &sle; in the
 form of a smaller, simpler, and more robust operating system, optimized for
 large, clustered deployments. It also features an atomic, transactional update
 mechanism, making the system more resilient against software-update-related
 problems.
</para>
 
 <para>
 &productname; automates the orchestration and management of
 containerized applications and services with powerful &kube; capabilities,
 including:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Workload scheduling places containers according to their needs while
   improving resource utilization. 
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Service discovery and load balancing provides an IP address for your
   services, and distributes load behind the scenes.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Application scaling up and down accommodates changing loads.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Non-disruptive rollout/rollback of new applications and updates enables
   frequent changes without downtime.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Health monitoring and management supports application self-healing and
   ensures application availability.
  </para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
 In addition, &productname; simplifies the platform operator’s experience, with
 everything you need to get up and running quickly, and to manage the
 environment effectively in production. It provides:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   A complete container execution environment, including a purpose-built
   container host operating system (&suse; &mos;), container runtime, and
   container image registries.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Enhanced datacenter integration features that enable you to plug &kube;
   into new or existing infrastructure, systems, and processes.    
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Application ecosystem support with &sle; container base images, and access
   to tools and services offered by &suse; Ready for CaaS Platform partners and
   the &kube; community.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   End-to-End security, implemented holistically across the full stack.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Advanced platform management that simplifies platform installation,
   configuration, re-configuration, monitoring, maintenance, updates,
   and recovery.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Enterprise hardening including comprehensive interoperability testing,
   support for thousands of platforms, and world-class platform maintenance and
   technical support.
  </para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
 You can deploy &productname; onto physical servers or use it on virtual
 machines. After deployment, it is immediately ready to run and provides a
 highly-scalable cluster.
</para>
<para>
 While &productname; inherits benefits of &sle; and uses tools and
 technologies well-known to system administrators such as
 <literal>cloud-init</literal> and Salt, the main innovation (compared to
 &sls;) comes with <emphasis role="bold">transactional updates</emphasis>. A
 transactional update is an update that can be installed when the system is
 running without any down-time. A transactional update can be rolled back, so
 if the update fails or is not compatible with your infrastructure, you can
 restore the previous system state.
</para>
<para>
 &productname; uses the &btrfs; file system with the following characteristics:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   The root file system and its snapshots are read-only.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Sub-volumes for data sharing are read-write.
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   &productname; introduces overlays of the <literal>/etc</literal> directories
   used by <literal>cloud-init</literal> and &salt;.
  </para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
 For more information, including a list of the various components which make up
 &productname; please refer to the Release Notes on <link
  xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/releasenotes/"/>.
</para>
</preface>
